Finding Aid for Mayer Zald papers, 1956-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mayer Zald papers 1956-2012, 1980-2008
Zald, Mayer N.
3 linear feet
2013031 Aa 2
Mayer Zald was a professor of social work, sociology and business administration at the University of Michigan from 1977 to 2001 when he retired. He continued to teach classes until 2012 and was the chair of the Sociology Department. The collection of his papers ranges from 1956-2012 (bulk 1980-2008) and includes biographical information, correspondence, and information about his contributions while working at the university. The majority of the collection is academic papers written by Zald.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Joan Zald (Donor number 10885 ) in January 2013.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open for research.
Mayer Nathan Zald was born on June 17, 1931 in Dearborn, Michigan and grew up in a Jewish middle and lower middle class neighborhood in the Detroit area. His father owned a clothing store in Ann Arbor but was bankrupt by the time Zald was born. His mother worked for the Michigan Employment Commission due to his father's recurring illness. As a teenager, Zald was heavily involved in a Jewish fraternity that dealt with intellectual and political debate. He worked in various manufacturing plants from age sixteen until he was twenty. He began his undergraduate work at Wayne State University in 1949 and then transferred in 1951 to the University of Michigan where he graduated with a B.A. degree in sociology in 1953. In 1955 he earned his Master's degree from the University of Hawaii and entered the Army. In 1956 he returned to the University of Michigan where he received his Ph.D. in 1961. He was a faculty member at the University of Chicago from 1960 to 1964, and in 1964 he moved to Nashville where he worked at Vanderbilt University until 1977.
Zald then began working at the University of Michigan as a professor in the Sociology Department. He served as chair of the Sociology Department at both Vanderbilt and Michigan in addition to serving as the Vice President of the American Sociological Association. He was also a member of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences and served on the boards of multiple professional journals in the sociology field, including his time as associate editor of the American Sociological Review from 1979 to 1982. His service as chair at the University of Michigan was from 1981 to 1986 and from 1990 to 1992. He also received the additional appointment as professor of business administration in 1989. Much of his research was focused on organizational studies, collective behavior, and social theory. He wrote 100 book chapters and articles, and 20 books. In 1989 he was awarded and presented at the Distinguished Senior Faculty Lecture. He retired from the Sociology Department at the University of Michigan in the spring of 2001 and was awarded professor emeritus status of social work and business administration. In 2008 he received the John D. McCarthy Award for Lifetime Achievement in the Scholarship of Social Movements and Collective Behavior from the Center for the Study of Social Movements and Social Change at the University of Notre Dame. After his retirement from the University of Michigan, he continued to teach a seminar at the University of Arizona. Zald passed away on August 7, 2012.
The Mayer Zald papers mostly consist of information during his time as a professor at the University of Michigan. The collection covers from 1956 to 2012, with the bulk being from 1980 to 2008. The collection is divided into five series: Biographical Information, Correspondence, Courses, Proposals, and Writings and Presentations.
Subjects:
Organizational sociology--Research.; Organizational sociology--Study and teaching.; University of Michigan. Department of Sociology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Zald, Mayer N.
- Biographical Information
  The Biographical Information series contains annual activity reports that Zald filed, information on the committees he was involved in, nominations he received, personal information including resume and curriculum vitae, a list of publications, and documentation from his time as chair of the Sociology Department.
  - Annual Reports 1984-1986, 1993-1999 (Box 1)
  - Committees 1980 (Box 1)
  - Nominations 1995-2010 (Box 1)
  - Library Collection 1999, 2002 (Box 1)
  - Personal Information 1963-2012 (Box 1)
  - Publications 1980-1985, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Sociology Chairman 1980-1990 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series contains letters and emails written to and from Zald and is organized chronologically.
  - 1974, 1976 (Box 1)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - 1981 (Box 1)
  - 1988, 1990 (Box 1)
  - 1993-1996 (Box 1)
  - 1999-2002 (Box 1)
  - 2004-2006 (Box 1)
  - 2008-2010 (Box 1)
- Courses
  - 200 Level 1975, 2008, undated (Box 1)
  - 400 Level 1977, 1983-1987 (Box 1)
  - 500 Level 2003 (Box 1)
  - 700-800 Level 2000, undated (Box 1)
  - Seminars 1993, 1995, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Sociology and Culture 1998-2001, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Sociology Department Review 1987 (Box 1)
- Proposals
  The Proposals series contains forms and information on various programs and funding opportunities that Zald applied to while working at the University of Michigan. Included are requests for funding sent to the National Science Foundation, the Russell Sage Foundation and the Guggenheim Foundation.
  - Advanced Management Institute 1999 (Box 1)
  - Interdisciplinary Courses 2002-2003, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - National Science Foundation 1999 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Memorial-Phoenix Project 1978 (Box 1)
  - Rockefeller and Guggenheim Foundations 1978-1987 (Box 1)
  - Russell Sage Foundation 1973, 1989, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Writings and Presentations
  The Writings and Presentations series contains book reviews that Zald wrote, as well as speeches and presentations that Zald gave at meetings, seminars, workshops, and lectures. Within this series are two subseries: Conferences and Writings. The Conferences subseries contains information on the various conferences that Zald attended or supported, as well as the presentations he gave at the conferences. The Writings subseries contains published and unpublished articles that Zald wrote, either individually or in conjunction with other scholars. In particular are a seemingly incomplete rough draft of his personal memoirs and his article "Social Movement Organizations: Growth, Decay, and Change" which is one of the top ten most frequently cited articles published in the journal Social Forces. Some of the writings are in the format they were published in, some are rough drafts, and some contain notes.
  - Charles Tilly Memorial 2008 (Box 2)
  - Conferences
    - Collective Behavior and Social Movements 1981-1983 (Box 2)
    - Corporate Social Responsibility 2007 (Box 2)
    - Embeddedness of Strategy 1995 (Box 2)
    - ICOS 1999-2000, 2006 (Box 2)
    - North Central Area AOS 1963 (Box 2)
    - Parsons Conference 1988 (Box 2)
    - Social Movement and Organizations 2000-2002 (Box 2)
    - Zaldfest 1999 (Box 2)
  - Distinguished Senior Faculty Lecture 2000-2001 (Box 2)
  - Gamson Roast 2011 (Box 2)
  - McCarthy Award 2006-2010 (Box 2)
  - North Central Association Meeting (Box 2)
  - Reviews 1959-2010, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Symposiums and Seminars 2005, 2008 (Box 2)
  - Workshops 2005, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Writings
    - Untitled (Box 2)
    - "A Note on the Usefulness and Validity of the Herbst Family Questionnaire," 1956 (Box 2)
    - "Administrative Regulation and Industry: A Sociological Perspective," 1979 (Box 2)
    - "America and the Rise of Social Movements," 1972 (Box 2)
    - "Appendix: The Trend of Social Movements in America: Professionalization and Resource Mobilization" (Box 2)
    - "Aspects of Racial Integration in the Methodist Church," 1966 (Box 2)
    - "Career Opportunities and Commitments Among Officers," 1964 (Box 2)
    - "Changing Movements, Changing Methods, and Changing Theories," 2007 (Box 2)
    - "Collective Actions and Protest in Organizations: History of an Idea," 2000 (Box 2)
    - "The Common Body of Knowledge for CPAs: Some Problems in Analysis," 1968 (Box 2)
    - "Compliance/Incentive Classifications of Organizations: Underlying Dimensions," 1977 (Box 2)
    - "Comparative Perspectives on Social Movements," 1996 (Box 2)
    - "The Corporate Coup d'Etat," 1978 (Box 2)
    - "The Correctional Institution for Juvenile Offenders: An Analysis of Organizational 'Character'," 1960 (Box 2)
    - "Covert Political Conflict in Organizations: Challenges From Below," 2002 (Box 2)
    - "Decentralization -- Myth vs. Reality," 1964 (Box 2)
    - "Disciplinary Trends, Inter-Disciplinary, and the Relationships of the Humanities and the Social Sciences," 2005 (Box 2)
    - "The Enduring Vitality of the Resource Mobilization Theory of Social Movements" (Box 2)
    - "External Events: The Context of Society and the Public Agenda Movement Outcome" (Box 2)
    - "Firms, Industries and Politics" (Box 2)
    - "From Commercial Elite to Political Administrator: The Recruitment of the Mayors of Chicago," 1965 (Box 2)
    - "The Future of Social Movements" (Box 2)
    - "Garbage Cans, Windows, and Social Movements on the Public Agenda," 1992 (Box 2)
    - "The Growth and Transformation of Educational Accrediting Agencies," 1968 (Box 2)
    - "History, Metanarratives, and Organizational Theory," 1999 (Box 2)
    - "History, Sociology, and Theories of Organization" (Box 2)
    - "Ideologically Structured Action: An Enlarged Agenda for Social Movement Research," 2000 (Box 2)
    - "Institutions in American Society," 1999 (Box 2)
    - "Institutions, Institutional Change, and Collective Action Potential," 2009 (Box 2)
    - Memoirs (Box 3)
    - "More Fragmentation? Unfinished Business in Linking the Social Sciences and the Humanities," 1996 (Box 3)
    - "Now We Are Almost Fifty! Reflections on a Theory of the Transformation of the Social Movement" (Box 3)
    - "On Organizational Niche and Adaptation" (Box 3)
    - "On the Social Control of Industries," 1978 (Box 3)
    - "On the Sociology of the Humanities: Collective Projects," 1989 (Box 3)
    - "Organizational Studies as a Scientific and Humanistic Enterprise: Toward a Reconceptualization of the Foundations of the Field," 1993 (Box 3)
    - "Organizations, Industry, and the State," 1988 (Box 3)
    - "Political Change, Citizenship Rights, and the Welfare State," 1985 (Box 3)
    - "The Power and Functions of Boards of Directors: A Theoretical Synthesis," 1969 (Box 3)
    - "Power Play: Social Movements, Collective Action and New Organizational Forms" (Box 3)
    - "Professions, Work and Organizations: Comments on the Contribution of Anselm Strauss," 1997 (Box 3)
    - "Progress and Cumulation in the Human Sciences After the Fall," 1995 (Box 3)
    - "Resource Mobilization Approach to the Study of Social Movements" (Box 3)
    - "Resource Mobilization as Theoretical Research Program and Epistemic Community," 2000 (Box 3)
    - "The Responsibility Paradox: Multinational Firms and Global Corporate Social Responsibility," 2006 (Box 3)
    - "Schumpeter and Organizational Intellectuals," 1973 (Box 3)
    - "The Social Construction of Causality: The Effects of Institutional Myths on Financial Regulation," 2010 (Box 3)
    - "Social Movement Industries: Competition and Conflict Among SMOs," 1980 (Box 3)
    - "Social Movement Organization: Growth, Decay and Change," 1965 (Box 3)
    - "Social Movement Sectors and Systemic Constraint," 1981 (Box 3)
    - "Social Movements and the Construction of New Organizational Forms," 1998 (Box 3)
    - "Social Movements and the Development of Health Care Institutions" (Box 3)
    - "Social Movements and the Transformation of American Health Care," 2010 (Box 3)
    - "Social Movements in Organizations: Coup d'Etat, Bureaucratic Insurgency, and Mass Movement," 1995 (Box 3)
    - "Sociological Classics and the Canon in the Study of Organizations," 2007 (Box 3)
    - "Sociology as a Discipline: Quasi-Science and Quasi-Humanities," 1987 (Box 3)
    - "The Sociology of Enterprise, Accounting and Budget Rules," 1984 (Box 3)
    - "Spinning Disciplines: Critical Management Studies in the Context of the Transformation of Management Education," 2001 (Box 3)
    - "The Structure of Society and Social Service Integration," 1969 (Box 3)
    - "Symbols into Plowshares: Dimensions of Organizational Incentives," 1975 (Box 3)
    - "Toward a Community of Apprentice Scholars" (Box 3)
    - "Toward a Permanent Revolution in the Graduate Curriculum," 1971 (Box 3)
    - "Transnational and International Social Movements in a Globalizing World" (Box 3)
    - "The Trend of Social Movements in America: Professionalization and Resource Mobilization," 1973 (Box 3)
    - "Undisciplining Organizational Studies: A Conversation Across Domains, Methods, and Beliefs," 1995 (Box 3)
    - "Vital Institutions," 1999 (Box 3)
    - "The Welfare State, Citizenship, and Bureaucratic Encounters," 1987 (Box 3)
    - "What Kind of Profession? Community Organization In and Beyond Social Work," 1997 (Box 3)
    - "Who Shall Rule? A Political Analysis of Succession in a Large Welfare Organization," 1965 (Box 3)
    - "The Wizards of Oz" (Box 3)
    - "The Y.M.C.A. and Urban Change," 1964 (Box 3)